Kate Harrison Friend papers, Inclusive: 1898-1950
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Kate Harrison Friend papers
Inclusive: 1898-1950
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
202
Friend, Kate Harrison
2 document boxes.
The Kate Harrison Friend papers consist of correspondence, literary manuscripts, scrapbooks, and photographs. The majority of the letters were to Kate Harrison Friend, philanthropist of Waco.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Friend was born in 1856 to Nathaniel and Arimenta (Harrison) in Boligee, Alabama. After the death of her father, Friend and her mother visited Waco, Texas, in 1885 and made it their permanent residence. Friend displayed an early commitment and interest in education. Upon her arrival to Waco, she and her mother opened a private school in their home. “Miss Kate,” as she was known in the community, put her education and writing skills to use by becoming the editor of Artesia, a local newspaper dedicated to Waco’s social scene. Later, she was hired as the Society Editor for the Waco Times-Herald. In 1897, Friend’s devotion to education led her to develop a junior Shakespeare class to study the writings of William Shakespeare. The success of the class led to the creation of the Waco Shakespeare Club in 1899, and it was recognized nationally after only one year of operation, in 1900. The same year, Friend’s dedication to Shakespeare led to her participation in a writing competition sponsored by the National Shakespeare Association. She won the grand prize of a trip to Stratford-upon-Avon. Upon her return, Friend published pamphlets on Shakespeare and the success of her writings led to her international recognition as a Shakespeare scholar.
Friend was an advocate for the better treatment of animals and saw a need in Waco for a well-organized animal shelter. She began a campaign for animal rights in 1902 and worked closely with the Waco Humane Society for forty-five years. Friend’s dedication to the humane treatment of animals won her a grant from Mrs. M. D. Ravenscroft of Santa Barbara, to build the Waco Animal Shelter. Additionally, Friend used her role within the Waco Humane Society to improve the treatment of women and children in the community. In 1926, Friend’s efforts led to the creation of a Human Agent position in the society whose purpose was to advocate for the neglected women, children, and animals of Waco.
Kate Friend served as the president of the Waco Federation, held a board position for the Texas Federation of Women’s Clubs from 1904-1936, and was editor of the Texas Federation News. Her involvement with the Texas Federation of Women’s Clubs led to increased support for drinking fountains in public schools and improvements in city parks. In fact, Friend’s support of city parks led to the donation of land from the William Cameron Family, which became Cameron Park. During World War II, she served as president of the Waco Women’s War Service Club. Kate Harrison Friend died on 1949 May 14 at the age of ninety-three.
Scope and Content
The Kate Harrison Friend papers begin in 1898 and ends in 1951. Records include correspondence, literary productions, scrapbooks, and photographic materials. The correspondence is exclusively letters written to Kate Harrison Friend. These letters provide insight about her vast involvement in varying activities in Texas. The literary production series describes Friend’s involvement in society as a whole through clipping and notes. Included are three literary outline studies of William Shakespeare’s plays, Coriolanus, King Lear, and Taming of the Shrew. The scrapbook series includes five books that have been compiled by Friend. Although the scrapbooks are in fair condition, each contains letters received by Friend from admirers, and insight on Friend’s interests and activities. The papers also include three matching photographs of Friend.
Arrangement
The Kate Harrison Friend papers are currently arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, II. Literary Productions, III. Scrapbooks, and IV. Photographs.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 202. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
Kelley, Dayton. The Handbook of Waco and McLennan County. Waco, Texas: Texian Press, 1972.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616.
Subjects (Organizations)
Shakespeare Club (Waco, Tex.); Texas Federation of Women's Clubs.; Waco Humane Society (Waco, Tex.)
Subjects
Artesia (Waco, Tex.: 1893).
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Programs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence, 1899-1951, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains letters written to Kate Harrison Friend. The majority of the content of the letters pertains to Friend’s literary outlines of three Shakespearean plays, Coriolanus, King Lear, and Taming of the Shrew, requests for copies of her written works, and thank you notes for her speaking engagements. The letters are mostly from admirers of Friend’s involvement with the Shakespeare Club and her work for the rights of women, children, and animals within the Waco community and McLennan County. This series is in average to good condition.
  - Correspondence, 1899-1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1903-1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1908-1911 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1919-1921, 1936, 1941, 1949-1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Literary Productions, 1855, 1899-1950, undated; 2
  These literary productions include clippings related to Kate Harrison Friends’ speaking engagements, awards, celebrations on her behalf, her involvement with the Shakespeare Club, Texas Federation of Women’s Clubs, the Waco Humane Society, and her death. Additionally, this series includes general notes written by Friend, minutes for the Women’s Club in Waco, and programs related to Texas Federation of Women’s Clubs conventions. Three outline studies written by Friend of Shakespeare’s plays Coriolanus, King Lear, and Taming of the Shrew are included. This series is in good condition.
  - Clippings, 1899-1901, 1904, 1910, 1916, 1928, 1940, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1949-1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings ( 1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clippings (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Outline Studies, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Programs (1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Programs (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Minutes: Texas Federation of Women’s Clubs, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Book: Shakespeare Writings, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Scrapbooks, 1898-1941; 3
  This series includes five scrapbooks that were compiled by Kate Harrison Friend. The scrapbooks contain clippings related to Friend’s activities, letters and notes written to Friend, invitations to Friend, and pamphlets related to engagements for the Shakespeare Club. This series is in fair to average condition
  - Scrapbook, 1898-1900 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook (1 of 2), 1900-1909, 1930, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook (2 of 2), 1900-1909, 1930, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1901-1903 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook (1 of 2), 1903-1904, 1906, 1913, 1915, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook (2 of 2), 1903-1904, 1906, 1913, 1915, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1911-1915 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Photographs, 1899-1900; 4
  This series includes three matted photographs of Kate Harrison Friend. This series is in good condition.
  - Photographs, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 9)